today we're going to talk about the
difference between a cpu and a gpu we
can tell the difference from the start
by looking at your name cpu is central
processing unit and gpu is graphics
processing unit okay so we have the
definitions but we know that gamers need
good gpus if they want their games to
run well
now the question here is why why do we
need a gpu isn't the cpu fast enough and
what about people that are using gpus
outside of gaming why are ai researchers
using gpu or what about bitcoin miners
why do they choose gpus over cpus does
that mean that gpus are faster than cpus
if that's true then why is intel still
in business we sell the intel stock and
buy nvidia stock only let's see a cpu is
i would say the most important part of
the computer is literally the brain the
cpu is the one in charge of talking to
the ram memory to put data or bring data
from there they also run all the code
that we write they are the ones that are
running our software they are also the
ones that talk to devices like a hard
drive or your keyboard for example again
the cpu is a really big deal for the
computer it is literally the brain
usually cpus can only handle one task at
a time which is already incredibly fast
but we humans want more speed so to
allow the cpu to sort of multitask we
gave the cpu multi-cores
a core is the one that handles
computation tasks like running the
program and doing all the logical
operations but with multi-core cpus the
brain of the computer is divided in soft
brains this allows the cpu to run more
than one task at a time one on each core
the intel core i9 extreme edition
processor has 18 cores and has a speed
of three gigahertz to understand how
fast that is we need to understand that
in cpus tasks are executed by cycles
simple instructions like getting data
from memory or writing data to memory
take one cycle to complete a core with
three gigahertz can run 3 billion cycles
per second with 18 cores that is 54
billion cycles per second that's insane
so if cpus are super fast then why do we
need gpus gpus also known as graphics
cards were created by nvidia in 1999 to
be used for computer graphics and image
processing initially the thing that
makes gpus different from cpus and what
makes them very well suited for image
processing in computer graphics is the
fact that a gpu is optimized to run many
tasks in parallel but hold on a second
because we just said that the intel core
i9 processor is also able to run many
tasks in parallel because it is
multi-core right
yes the intel cpu is multi-core but it
is not multi-core enough for example the
nvidia geoforce 3090 graphics card has
cores and each core has a speed of 1.7
gigahertz which means that the card is
running more than 17
trillion cycles per second if you
compare 17 trillion with the miserable
54 billion cycles that we get from intel
it looks like we have a winner now the
question is why aren't they putting more
cores in the cpu 18 cores from intel
compared to more than 10 000 cores from
nvidia is an embarrassment what is intel
doing are they asleep should i get a
refund of all the intel stock that i
bought the reason why the gpu can have
more than 10 000 cores while intel can
only push to 18 cores is because the
cores of the gpu and the cpu are not the
same cpu cores have a bigger set of
instructions they can do more things
this is also why intel can only fit 18
in their processor because they're also
super power hungry this is because gpu
cores are in contrast designed to
perform a smaller range of operations
mostly math operations with vectors and
matrix multiplications but very fast and
at the same time in parallel this is why
gpus are used for rendering graphics or
image manipulation the gpu is able to do
the number crushing required to do the
calculations for all the pixels in the
screen at the same time for example if
we have an image with 12 million pixels
let's say and we say that we want to
double the size of the image we want to
resize the image it means that we have
to multiply each pixel of that image by
two this is a simple operation multiply
by two but because we have to do this
for each pixel in the screen at the same
time this task will be better handled by
the gpu and that's actually a dumb
example actual calculations done by gpus
when working with 3d images like in a
video game are way more complex than
that for example in a 3d video game a
gpu might be calculating what is the
amount of light that is reflecting from
an object taking into account the
material and the texture from the object
and also taking into account the angle
of the light as well as the camera
position on the scene and then the gpu
has to take all this 3d coordinates and
translate them from a 3d space to a 2d
image that the screen is able to display
that's a lot of number crunching
now if the video game is running at 60
frames per second that means that that
calculation has to happen 60 times per
second all the time at the same time
that's a lot
gpus are very good at solving problems
that are embarrassingly parallel that's
their real name an embarrassing parallel
problem is a problem that requires
little to no effort to be divided in
multiple tasks that can be executed in
parallel which brings us to the next
part the areas where gpus are being used
apart from video games and image
manipulation
an area that can benefit a lot from
parallel computation which is what the
gpu provides is ai for example because
training a machine learning model is a
task that can be accomplished in
parallel gpus are the perfect tool for
the job and they will make the training
process faster than if it was done using
a cpu this usage of graphic cards used
for something apart from gaming is
what's known as gp gpu which means
general purpose computing on gpus and
it's an area that explores all the
different computation problems that can
be solved using gpus like for example
scientific research astronomical
research biology research all those
things so now that we understand the
difference between a cpu and a gpu and
now that we know how gpus can be used in
different areas apart from learning let
me tell you about the sponsor of today's
video ktcloud would like to let you know
about their new hyperscale ai computing
service with hyperscale you can run your
code on gpu powered servers which as we
know is something you would need if you
are training your ai models for example
the problem is that gpu servers are
expensive in linux for example the
smallest gpu server that you can rent
costs a thousand dollars a month and you
have to pay whether you use it or not
but the cool thing about hyperscale is
that you only have to pay for the time
that your code is using the gpus which
means that if you only use the gpus for
10 minutes you are going to pay for 10
minutes only in other server providers
when your ai model grows and you need
more gpu power you usually have to
change servers which means re-uploading
the code which could be very annoying
with hyperscale you don't have to change
servers because hyperscale is going to
scale based on the resources that you
need gpu resources and gpu clusters can
be expanded as much as you want usually
you will have to refactor your code if
you want to run in the gpu to take
advantage of all the multiple cores and
the parallelism but with hyperscale this
power distribution happens out of the
box which means that you don't have to
refactor your code but you will still be
able to take full advantage of the power
of the gpu if you want to learn more and
you want to try hyperscale ai computing
service please click the link below
where you will be able to register for a
free hands-on seminar provided by kt
thanks to katie for sponsoring this
video and thank you for watching this
video let me know in the comments what
do you think of this video and what
video you would like to see next and i
will make my best to make it happen stay
happy stay free stay healthy eat kimchi
come zamida salon hey yo see you on the
next one bye